<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>public opinion on Justin Murphy</title>
    <link>https://jmrphy.net/tags/public-opinion/</link>
    <description>Recent content in public opinion on Justin Murphy</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Justin Murphy</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://jmrphy.net/tags/public-opinion/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Use recursive partitioning and decision trees to guess someone&#39;s political opinions (using R with survey data)</title>
      <link>https://jmrphy.net/post/recursive-partitioning-decision-trees-guess-opinions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jmrphy.net/post/recursive-partitioning-decision-trees-guess-opinions/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you meet someone at a dinner party, and you really want to know their opinion about some juicy political topic. If you’re me, you might just ask them straight up. But often, there are reasons why you can’t be so forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, political opinions are not randomly distributed. So if you can glean a few facts about someone, you can often predict their other, more hidden opinions. The challenge is knowing which pieces of small-talk are the most predictive of the jucier questions you can’t quite ask them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe you only have one minute; which questions should you ask? In what order should you ask them? If there’s no time limit, how many questions should you ask before you’re wasting your time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ideal solution would be a short list of questions, in a particular order, like a tree: If they say yes to this, then ask them this, and so on. Ideally, this list would be as short and simple as necessary to make the best guess possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out there is a statistical technique that matches this challenge perfectly. Recursive partitioning is a technique that produces decision trees of binary or “yes/no” questions. The resulting decision tree represents the statistically optimal path of questioning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-to-conduct-recursive-partitioning-in-r&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to conduct recursive partitioning in R&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you want to predict whether or not someone supports the suppression of racist speakers. A bit akward to ask straight up at a dinner party. We can use a large public dataset such as the General Social Survey, run some recursive partitioning, and obtain the “tree” of mundane questions we can respectably ask someone at a dinner party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, identify the variable of interest. In the GSS, there is a variable that asks whether racist speakers should be allowed to speak or not. The name of the variable is &lt;em&gt;spkrac.&lt;/em&gt; (In my processing, I renamed this variable &lt;em&gt;spkrac.fac&lt;/em&gt;.) Then identify the variables representing mundane facts you can observe yourself or reasonably ask about within the norms of small talk. I identified the following mundane variables (for more information, search for the GSS codebook):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sex/gender = variable named &lt;strong&gt;sex&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;race = variable named &lt;strong&gt;race&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;left/right identification = variable named &lt;strong&gt;pol&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;family income = variable named &lt;strong&gt;realinc&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;college attendance = variable named &lt;strong&gt;college&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;word knowledge or verbal skill (proxy for IQ) = variable named &lt;strong&gt;wordsum&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-to-conduct-recursive-partitioning-for-a-binary-dependent-variable-in-r&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;How to conduct recursive partitioning for a binary dependent variable in R&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, our variable of interest is a binary variable: one either allows or disallows racist speakers. The modeling routines are different for different variables of interest, but so long as your variable of interest is binary, you can more or less follow the following routine. The code is commented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First we need to import the raw GSS data and process the variables we’ll be using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Import the necessary packages
require(tidyverse)
require(haven)
require(knitr)
require(rpart)
require(rpart.plot)


gssFullPanel &amp;lt;- read_dta(&amp;quot;/Users/justin/Dropbox/Public/political-data/GSS7218_R1.dta&amp;quot;)

df &amp;lt;- subset(gssFullPanel,
                 select = c(sex, educ, realinc, 
             polviews, spkrac, race, ethnic, wordsum))

# Race
# Optional: Assign NA to other because it&amp;#39;s ambiguous and wildly unstable over time
# factor() removes empty factor levels, which is useful here because IAP = 0
df$race&amp;lt;-factor(df$race)
levels(df$race) &amp;lt;- c(&amp;quot;White&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;Black&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;Other&amp;quot;)
# levels(df$race)[levels(df$race)==&amp;#39;Other&amp;#39;] &amp;lt;- NA

# Sex
# as_factor() from haven package brings in the labels for factor levels
df$sex&amp;lt;-as_factor(df$sex)
levels(df$sex) &amp;lt;- c(&amp;quot;Male&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;Female&amp;quot;)

# College
df$college &amp;lt;- ifelse(as.numeric(df$educ)&amp;lt;=12,
                     &amp;quot;No College&amp;quot;,
                     &amp;quot;At Least Some College&amp;quot;)
df$college &amp;lt;- factor(df$college,
                     levels=c(&amp;quot;No College&amp;quot;, 
                              &amp;quot;At Least Some College&amp;quot;))

df$spkrac.fac &amp;lt;- factor(df$spkrac -1) # Reduce to 0 and 1 and convert to factor
levels(df$spkrac.fac)&amp;lt;-c(&amp;quot;Allowed&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Not Allowed&amp;quot;) # Rename levels

df$pol &amp;lt;- as_factor(df$polviews)
df$pol &amp;lt;- dplyr::recode(df$pol,
                            &amp;quot;EXTREMELY LIBERAL&amp;quot; = &amp;quot;Extremely Liberal&amp;quot;,
                            &amp;quot;liberal&amp;quot; = &amp;quot;Liberal&amp;quot;,
                            &amp;quot;SLIGHTLY LIBERAL&amp;quot; = &amp;quot;Slightly Liberal&amp;quot;,
                            &amp;quot;moderate&amp;quot; = &amp;quot;Moderate&amp;quot;,
                            &amp;quot;SLGHTLY CONSERVATIVE&amp;quot; = &amp;quot;Slightly Conservative&amp;quot;,
                            &amp;quot;conservative&amp;quot; = &amp;quot;Conservative&amp;quot;,
                            &amp;quot;EXTRMLY CONSERVATIVE&amp;quot; = &amp;quot;Extremely Conservative&amp;quot;,
                            .default = NA_character_)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we can conduct the partitioning. The code is pretty simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Start by subsetting your main dataset (&amp;quot;df&amp;quot;) to just the variables
# of interest. We&amp;#39;ll also omit any rows with missing values.
sub&amp;lt;-df %&amp;gt;%
  select(c(&amp;quot;spkrac.fac&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;sex&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;race&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;pol&amp;quot;,
           &amp;quot;realinc&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;college&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;wordsum&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;%
  na.omit()


# Next conduct the recursive partitioning using the rpart() function
# Variable of interest first, then a &amp;quot;~&amp;quot;, as follows:
fit &amp;lt;- rpart(spkrac.fac ~ sex + race + pol + college + realinc + wordsum,
             # With small data, set &amp;#39;minsplit&amp;#39;and &amp;#39;cp&amp;#39; to low values
             control=rpart.control(minsplit=2, cp=0.001),
             method=&amp;quot;class&amp;quot;, # if you&amp;#39;re predicting a class, rather than a number
             data=sub)

# Now &amp;quot;prune the tree&amp;quot; with cross-validation, aka keep only the branches
# with the most predictive value
pfit&amp;lt;- prune(fit, cp=fit$cptable[which.min(fit$cptable[,&amp;quot;xerror&amp;quot;]),&amp;quot;CP&amp;quot;])

# Plot the decision tree
rpart.plot(pfit,
yesno=2, # add yes/no labels
box.palette=&amp;quot;GnBu&amp;quot;, # add a swankier color palette
shadow.col=&amp;quot;gray&amp;quot;,
tweak=1.1, # increase the font size a bit
main=&amp;quot;Decision Tree Predicting If Someone Wants to Suppress Racist Speakers&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jmrphy.net/post/2019-12-05-how-to-use-recursive-partitioning-and-decision-trees-to-guess-someone-s-political-opinions_files/figure-html/partitioning-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;interpretation&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Interpretation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interpretation is very intuitive. The top of the tree is the first question you should ask, the single variable that gives you the most leverage to predict your victim’s secret opinion. The top node represents your knowledge before asking them anything: If you meet a random person, there is a 38% chance they would vote to suppress racist speakers. This applies to the whole population of America (100%.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the analysis, the first question with the most predictive power is: “Did you ever go to college?” If they say yes, the probability of them wanting to suppress drops to 29% and that’s all you need to ask them! Nothing else will improve your guess (at least from the variables we selected).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If they never went to college, the next question you have to ask yourself is whether they’re smart. You probably don’t want to give them a vocabulary test, but conversation is pretty naturally revealing. So if they are on the dumb side, consider them a “no” in this chart. If they are smart, then you infer with a 40% probablility that they would disallow the speaker (you infer that they would allow). If they are dumb, it’s now a coin flip (and 26% of the population is here).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, what is their race? This you can probably guess yourself. From here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If they are white, then there’s a 48% chance they would disallow the speaker. If then they are male, there’s a 45% chance they would disallow and that’s your final guess (that they would allow). If they are female, you can see if their family is rich or not. If rich, they are slightly less likely than a coin flip to disallow the speaker (46%); if poor, they’re slightly more likely than a coin flip to disallow the speaker (54%).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If they are dumb and non-white,then there’s a 57% chance they would not allow the speaker. And that’s your best guess.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;conclusion&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a relatively small dataset, the results strike me as reasonably useful (and intuitively plausible). To gauge this, consider that a “yes” to our first question (whether they attended any college) gives us a pretty good bet that our interlocutor would allow racist speakers (71%), and that represents about 50% of people! With only a few more questions, two of which we can observe without asking, we can get to as much as a 57% guess that they would disallow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably the major limitation of this short study is that we don’t get very impressive traction on those who would disallow racist speakers. The highest we get is a 57% probability, which is non-trivially better than if we know nothing about someone (in which case we’d guess a 38% probability). But it’s still not great. All this means is that we need better predictor variables, which we could identify through additional research. But as a first cut with a small handful of variables I gathered based only on my own intuitions, these results are pretty good, I think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most interesting implication here is that ideological identification totally drops out! It appears that it’s not predictive. This is fascinating, given that many people today tend to think of speech suppression is a fashion on the educated Left! And it is, but that’s only a highly visible minority. Political scientists would not be surprised by this result: We’ve long known that leftists and educated people are always more supportive of free expression (you just don’t hear about those people in the media right now).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next time you’re at a party, please try this. Let me know how it works!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Does Media Coverage Drive Public Support for UKIP or Does Public Support for UKIP Drive Media Coverage?</title>
      <link>https://jmrphy.net/publication/bjps/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jmrphy.net/publication/bjps/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The link between public opinion and public policy</title>
      <link>https://jmrphy.net/blog/2014/02/15/some-questions-about-the-opinion-policy-link/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jmrphy.net/blog/2014/02/15/some-questions-about-the-opinion-policy-link/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Early theorists in modern political science had high hopes for using new survey techniques to analyze the individual-level psychological and behavorial processes which constitute modern liberal democracy. Berelson (1952), for instance, noted that democratic theory assumes that citizens meet certain requirements related to tolerance, patience, interest, knowledge, and the will to participate. See also the famous book &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2C96WGA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Voting&lt;/em&gt; (Berelson, Lazarsfeld, and McPhee 1954)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But early research in political behavior was bleak. Seminal citations for this view are &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2Fh74Cu&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The American Voter&lt;/em&gt; (Campbell et al. 1960)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2EGmAec&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Converse (1964)&lt;/a&gt;. Most people were found to have little knowledge of politics, most political opinions were not based on facts, most people were generally authoritarian and prejudiced, they typically only listened to views they already agreed with, and participation in politics was low (Prothro and Grigg 1960; McCloskey 1964; Cobb and Elder 1971, 893). In short, much of this first wave of political science research, largely based on the new survey methods growing popular at the time, would have seemed damning evidence that the citizens of the United States&amp;rsquo; simply do not constitute what is called democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than take these studies as ammunition to protest the US political system&amp;ndash;and perhaps joining the students, the blacks, and the women who at this very time &lt;em&gt;were&lt;/em&gt; doing precisely this&amp;ndash;the next wave of political scientists simply argued that early theorists of democracy had too narrow a definition of democracy. The new idea was that &amp;ldquo;democracy&amp;rdquo; only requires an empirical relationship between public opinion and policymaking &lt;em&gt;in the aggregate&lt;/em&gt;. If the actual direction of state policymaking were to show zero correlation with shifts in public opinion, this would be damning evidence that what the public wants has no affect on the policies pursued by state elites. But so long as policymaking in general moves in response to aggregate public opinion, this is adequate evidence that the &amp;ldquo;macropolity&amp;rdquo; is indeed a functioning democracy. And indeed, since then, political scientists have found that in democracies, shifts in public opinion tend to be followed by corresponding shifts in policymaking. Many scholars interpert these findings as evidence that democratic institutions deliver what they&amp;rsquo;re supposed to: mass public control over the general direction of national policymaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As scholars pointed out even at the time, it is a very conservative move to solve the problem of undemocratic realities by simply weakening the definition of democracy (Easton 1969; Walker 1966; Bachrach 1967). I&amp;rsquo;m interested in specifying and, in the future, measuring and testing two specific aspects of this politically and therefore scientifically problematic move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.) I hypothesize that a crucial unjustified problem at this moment in political science, a theoretical and empirical problem never yet adequately addressed and which bears extraordinary significance for true popular social change, is that &lt;em&gt;what people express as their opinion is significantly determined by what the status quo institutions at that moment will permit.&lt;/em&gt; This is because in general, people do not express political demands for policy changes which they believe are impossible given the institutional landscape. Such an articulation is seen as stupid, naive, or simply meaningless, so individuals calculate and articulate their political desires in a way that effectively assumes the institutional status quo &lt;em&gt;as given&lt;/em&gt;. In this way, discourse on the level of &amp;ldquo;public opinion&amp;rdquo; (e.g., asking people questions about what a current government should do) contains an &amp;ldquo;approval&amp;rdquo; of the status quo which is not real but is simply assumed into their answer by the nature of the question. Political science since this period essentially imputes to citizens a baseline level of &amp;ldquo;support&amp;rdquo; for a status quo which is really nothing more than their degree of capitulation to a status quo which (variably and contingently) presents itself as given and unmovable. These two components&amp;ndash;sincere approval of the status quo and mere compliance with power (the very nature of which is to be taken as given)&amp;ndash;have never been adequately disaggregated. Public opinion has only ever been, from its beginning, a measured aggregate response to questions which are generated in part by an unmeasured quantum of political force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this light, we might begin to hypothesize that political practices such as delegation, the proliferation of subnational and/or supranational bureacracies charged with certain policymaking imperatives and/or prohibitions, have more to do with public opinion than is typically thought. For instance, the European Commission was designed to be the &amp;ldquo;engine&amp;rdquo; of European integration precisely because it would be insulated from the snags of domestic resistances. We might hypothesize that the establishment of a bureaucratically insulated policymaking institution such as the EC (or any other sub- or supra-national institution which removes a portion of policymaking power from democratic control) lowers the salience of certain public opinion questions and/or decreases the tendency of citizens to articulate certain approvals or disapprovals. Political scientists such as Timothy Hellwig have shown that citizens do indeed discount their judgments of the political landscape based on exogenous changes such as economic globalization, but this logic ought to apply to any institutional change with any effect on what it is possible for certain actors to do or not do. Specifically, purposeful institutional innovations might have the effect of ameliorating citizens negative judgments of certain actors or other previously existing institutions, or perhaps they might diffuse blame across so many institutions that citizens no longer feel dissatisfied with any of them. More specifically in our example, the advent of the EC might weaken citizens&amp;rsquo; negative judgments of domestic policymakers, if they believe domestic policymakers have a weaker institutional role in setting policy than before the advent of the EC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers will have to disaggregate these &amp;ldquo;authentic-individual&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;forced-institutional&amp;rdquo; components of public opinion data before we can take them seriously as reflections of genuine support or disapproval of the political status quo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.) Another extraordinary threat to this already conservative rationalization of contemporary public policymaking is the possibility that public opinion is itself determined by political and economic elites. For, of course, if changes in public opinion were found to be determined by status quo political factors not democratically determined (distinct from and in addition to the baseline bias caused by institutions, outlined above), then even robust correlations between aggregate public opinion and policymaking could no longer be taken seriously as evidence of democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the claim of critics such as David Harvey. They point to the 1970s as a crucial period. The example of Lewis Powell&amp;rsquo;s memo to the US Chamber of Commerce (Harvey 2005, 43). The Chamber of Commerce and National Association of Manufacturers began a significant and documented intensification of its spending, lobbying, and membership. The Business Roundtable is founded in 1972. Corporate interests start funding a large group of think-tanks and academic institutions as well. NBER is an example. The Trilateral commission in 1973, the report by political scientists called &amp;ldquo;The Crisis of Democracy.&amp;rdquo; Nozick, Milton Freedom on TV. Of course, this remains to be demonstrated very convincingly in the quantitative literature, but I should like to try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even the mainstream &amp;ldquo;public policy&amp;rdquo; literature testifies to the fact that &amp;ldquo;political marketing&amp;rdquo; has as much to do with selling political products, i.e. producing political ideas, as gauging what citizens demand (Lees-Marshment 2011, 9). They quite openly and uncontroversially use techniques of manipulation, taken from advertising and marketing. So it is hardly a fringe left-wing idea that public opinion is the object as much as it is the subject of policymakers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
