<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>mechanisms on Justin Murphy</title>
    <link>/tags/mechanisms/</link>
    <description>Recent content in mechanisms on Justin Murphy</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Justin Murphy</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/mechanisms/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The affective politics of keeping it real</title>
      <link>/blog/2017/06/20/the-affective-politics-of-keeping-it-real/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2017/06/20/the-affective-politics-of-keeping-it-real/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It once made sense for professional intellectuals to bite their tongue in exchange for the influence they could gain by conforming to the dominant language. For a while, this was arguably rational and defensible—perhaps even a game-theoretic necessity for anyone sincerely interested in cultivating a genuinely public and political intellectual project. While it’s obvious the internet has changed the game, old stereotypes die hard and continue to constrain human potential well after their objective basis has disappeared. In particular, the contemporary stereotype of the public intellectual as a self-possessed professional who regularly appears in “the media” to speak on public affairs in the royal language, is a contingent product of the postwar rise of mass broadcasting (one-to-many) media. In much of the postwar period, the classic “mass media”—newspapers, radio, television—had extremely large, mass audiences and where characterized by high costs of entry. This technical and economic environment offered huge rewards for speaking the dominant language within the paramaters of respectable opinion. It was probably with cable television that a centrifugal tendency began the processes of fragmentation, polarization, and decentralization that would eventually bring us to where we are today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, there is no longer any mass audience to speak to through dominant channels, overwhelming majorities do not trust mass media, and even the cognitively fragmented semi-mass audiences that remain will only listen to what they already think. Not to mention the masses probably have less power today than anytime in the twentieth century, so why bother even trying to speak to the masses? As a young academic, if I play by the rules for the next 10 years so that I might be respected by influential academics or gain access to regularly speaking on BBC or something like that, I would have sacrificed all of my creative energy for quite nearly nothing. As far as I can tell, today, the idea of biding your time as a young and respectable intellectual, to one day earn a platform of political significance, appears finally and fully obsolete. In one sense, this is already obvious to the millions who long ago stopped following mainstream media and long ago lost all respect for academic credentials; but in another sense, an overwhelming number of human beings continue to think, speak, and behave as if we are still operating in this old world, as if there is some reason to not say everything one feels like saying, as if there is some social or political or economic reward that will come toward the end of a respectable career of professional self-restraint. It’s easy for autodidacts and natural outsiders to say, “Duh, we told you so,” but this in no way comprehends or solves the really striking and politically significant puzzle that an extraordinary degree of human power remains &lt;em&gt;voluntarily repressed&lt;/em&gt; for rewards and punishments that no longer exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as the self-restrained professional intellectual is shaped by the rewards of a media environment long dead, so too are they shaped by punishments which are little more than paranoid fears. Many academics and professionals believe that for the sake of their careers they must exercise the utmost discretion in what they put online, and they confidently tell young people to exercise the same discretion for the sake of their own futures. But the reality is almost the exact opposite. First of all, with some important exceptions of course, nobody gives a shit about what you put on the internet. Nobody with any power over you has the time to follow, and the few that do won’t care enough about you to follow or dig very much. In my now slightly above-average history of recklessly posting to the internet, before and after getting a competitive professional job, the worst that has ever happened is that nobody cares (and that’s most of the time). But the best that has happened, here and there, is that a lot of people care and appreciate it and new friends are made and all kinds of new paths appear, individually and collectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The self-restraining, strategic professional intellectual is not only operating on incorrect beliefs but beliefs which are almost exactly inverse to the truth: today, playing by rules of respectability is perhaps the straightest path to unemployment and impotent resentment, while simply &lt;em&gt;cultivating the capacity to say or do something real&lt;/em&gt; (by definition prohibited by respectability), is a necessary (and sometimes even sufficient) condition for being genuinely valued by anyone, anywhere. Obviously if you have certain dimensions of poor character (i.e. you’re a racist or something) then reckless posting to the internet will likely, and perhaps rightly, lead to many negative consequences. But if you’re a basically decent person who just wants to push a little harder on what you really think, what you really feel, your experiences or your interests, or even just fuck around, the conventional wisdom still drastically overestimates the punishments and underestimates the rewards of doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these comments feel to you outdated because you think all of this already happened years ago with the initial rise of the internet, I would say you underestimate the quantity of human beings (and the qualitative intensities they could produce), who have yet to fully update their beliefs and behaviors around these matters. In some sense, the United States only just now, in 2016, elected its first President of the internet age. The fact that millions of people are genuinely perplexed and horrified by what is happening in this regard, is an index of how little the internet’s rewiring of power circuits has actually been integrated in the perceptions, beliefs, and behaviors of most people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If political theory will ever be a world-historical causal factor in the radically fragmented and decentralized age of information, I believe it will at least partially have to consist in living, interpersonal transmissions of &lt;em&gt;what works&lt;/em&gt; to produce power within concrete, available situations. I suppose it is on that belief that I am reflecting on matters such as the micro-politics of self-expression, with some personal context as anecdotal data. I believe there exist objective, micro-political mechanisms whereby &lt;em&gt;being real&lt;/em&gt; generates &lt;em&gt;real power&lt;/em&gt;; that many people under-estimate or mistrust the objective reality of this mechanism; that many people live under compliant resentment because of incorrect beliefs about how the macro-social institutional environment will respond to their idiosyncratic deviations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I speak about myself at all, it’s not because I’m special or great but precisely because I am nothing, nobody, yet it has always been in learning how to become nobody that I seem to unlock whatever few real powers now possess me. I’m a young nobody academic or writer or whatever, I’m not famous or influential in academia or even on the internet, but I have been able to cultivate and maintain an energetic, autonomous, creative intellectual life that feels to me on the right track intellectually and politically, by what I think is a more accurate but still uncommon map of our immediate strategic environment, combined with periodically forcing myself to push outward on what feels to be in some way not allowed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have almost come to see this as a methodological principle—wherever you genuinely think or observe or desire to do something that you would be vaguely punished socially for saying/doing at a dinner party, then saying/doing that on the internet almost always produces immanent power and its by-product joy; it almost always clears debilitating noise and advances one of the threads that make-up the continiuty of one’s life. The entire life orientation that believes facing toward power is the image of intellectual and political sophistication—this, in my view, is the spitting image of mystified contemporary complicity. If I am trying to share how I think all of this works, and how I have experienced it, it is because I dream of what would happen if thousands of highly capable intellects currently toiling under institutional respectability suddenly realized they have no reason to self-censor and everything to gain from simply disarming their objectively miscalibrated expression calculators.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The psychology of prohibiting outside thinkers</title>
      <link>/blog/2017/05/15/psychology-of-prohibiting-outside-thinkers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2017/05/15/psychology-of-prohibiting-outside-thinkers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Why do so many respectable, intellectually oriented people (academics, artists, and activists) wish to exclude independent right-wing intellectual work on moral grounds? I have in mind several recent campaigns to ensure some right-wing writer/artist, not be allowed to speak or perform in some venue. I am going to make a general theoretical point about a widespread social phenomenon, but I should also be honest about the specific individuals and institutions I see as motivating case studies. I have in mind the campaign to &lt;a href=&#34;https://shutdownld50.tumblr.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;shut down the LD50 gallery&lt;/a&gt;, and the decision of The New Centre for Research &amp;amp; Practice to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/thenewcentre/posts/644026572465531&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;remove Nick Land from its roster of lecturers&lt;/a&gt;. I don&amp;rsquo;t know these people, and I have nothing against them personally. I have no interest in impugning them or &amp;ldquo;calling them out,&amp;rdquo; I would much rather enjoy thinking with them; the problem is that these are precisely cases of closing that door, on &amp;ldquo;progressive&amp;rdquo; grounds that appear dishonest, cowardly, and conservative. So although I have no ill will, the only way to think about door-closers is from the outside of their door, e.g. about them, rather than with them. These campaigns and institutional decisions, and so many public pronouncements by other “progressive” actors, present themselves as efforts to protect the public sphere from violent or harmful effects, but it’s increasingly impossible to believe that this is the real motivation. There is a widespread fallacy, what we might call the ad hominem fallacy fallacy, that it’s unreasonable to question someone’s motivations. It may be unreasonable to dismiss someone’s arguments by impugning their motivations, but it’s very reasonable to theorize someone’s motivations as on object of interest in its own right—&lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; when the stated motivations are increasingly belied by the effects they repeatedly produce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to offer a concrete, informal theoretical account of what institutional intellectuals are really doing when they pull-up their draw-bridges to independent right-wing intellectuals such as Nick Land. Very simply, they are imposing a &lt;em&gt;cordon sanitaire&lt;/em&gt; that is instrumentally necessary to the continuation of their unjustified intellectual privileges in the institutional order. I am increasingly convinced there is simply no other public function to this political repetition compulsion. The reason this is important, from the left, is that this &lt;em&gt;cordon sanitaire&lt;/em&gt; is straightforwardly a mechanism to conserve the status quo, everything progressives pretend to be interested in overthrowing. This is why neo-reactionary intellectuals speak of the status quo political order as dominated by a left-progressive “Cathedral,” and this post will provide one example of why I think they are correct to do so. In this way, genuine left revolutionaries will sooner than later learn to take heed from some of these right-wing diagnoses about what is rotten in left culture. If you believe in radical equality and collective liberation from unjust institutions, from the left, you have to be able to see how your compulsions might be a function of this Cathedral more than you care to admit. As someone who currently possesses bourgeois intellectual privileges, and as someone who believes in equality (i.e., I know I am not ultimately superior to many others who lack my platform), I wish to be perfectly clear about how these mechanisms function, as someone who bears witness to them introspectively. If it is still possible to be a genuinely radical intellectual committed to collective liberation, this is the least it will require.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, it seems to be a fact that the genuinely intellectual wings of the alt-right or neo-reaction (NRx) or whatever you want to call it, are probably too intelligent and sophisticated for bourgeois intellectual workers to engage with, let alone compete with. The reason I know this is because I have only been able to really explore this world with the privilege of my sabbatical; bourgeois intellectual workers typically just don’t have the time to read a bunch of long essays on the internet. So if those essays are actually pretty smart and a legitimate challenge to your institutional authority as a credentialed intellectual—you are functionally required to close ranks, if only with a silent agreement to not engage. As an academic political scientist, I have at least average comfort with the history of political thought, yet when I really peruse all the independent NRx intellectuals, if I’m being honest I’d have to admit that I would need to go back to the books to really grok and engage what some of them are trying to say. I am on research leave and I don’t even have the time (or interest) in really doing that as deeply as would be required to engage all of it meaningfully. This is how I can very confidently call bullshit on any currently full-time bourgeois symbol-manipulator who pretends to know with any confidence the alleged uselessness or harmfulness of the NRx intellectual ecology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as soon as anyone from this non-institutional world produces effects within the institutional orbit, it is actually a really serious survival reflex for all institutionally privileged intellectuals to play the morality card (“no platform!”). If all these strange, outside autodidacts are actually smart and independently producing high-level intellectual content you don’t have the time to even understand, let alone defeat or otherwise control, this is an existential threat to your entire livelihood. Because all of your personal identity, your status, and your salary, is based directly on your credentialed, legitimated membership card giving your writings and pontifications an officially sanctioned power and authority. If that door is opened even a crack by non-credentialed outsiders, the whole jig is up for the respectable bourgeois monopoly on the official intellectual organs of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting question is, because respectable intellectuals are often pretty smart and capable, why are they so fearful of outside intellectual projects, even if they are as evil as some fear? They are smart and capable intellectuals, so you’d think they would embrace some interesting challenge as an opportunity for productive contestation. Why don’t they? Well, here’s where the reality gets ugly. The reason respectable intellectuals so instinctively close ranks around the moral exclusion of NRx intellectuals is that currently working, respectable intellectuals privately know that the intellectual compromises they have made to secure their respectability and careers has rendered most of their life’s work sadly and vulnerably low-quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To convince status-quo cultural money dispensers to give you a grant, for instance, any currently “successful” academic or artist has to so extensively pepper their proposal with patently stupid words and notions that knowingly make the final result a sad, contorted piece of work 80% of which is bent to the flattery of our overlords. But we falsely rationalize this contortion as “mature discipline” which we then rationalize to be the warrant for our privileged status as legitimate intellectuals. This is just good old fashioned conservatism, the standard psychology of bourgeois hypocrisy that is the molecular basis for the stability of a capitalist society organized around unjust and unequal exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we know deep down inside that our life’s work is only half of what it could have been had we the courage to not ask for permission, if there ever arise people who are doing high-level intellectual work on the outside, exactly as they wish to without anyone’s permission or money, then not only are we naturally resentful, but we secretly know that at least some of these outsiders are likely doing more interesting, more valuable, more radically incisive work than we are, because we secretly know that we earn our salary by agreeing to only say half of what we could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Aside: The only reason I’m psychologically and sociologically capable of writing this is precisely because through the internet I am shifting a large share of my eggs into the basket of the outside, instead of writing grant bids that actively make me less interesting and less honest; and I am young enough in my academic career that my sunk costs and interpersonal investments in academic networks are sufficiently low that I can admit these realities without too much pain.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the entire social value and self-esteem of respectable intellectuals is premised on this &lt;em&gt;guilty conscience&lt;/em&gt;, moral opposition is the most immediately natural and useful symbolic flagpole around which a &lt;em&gt;cordon sanitaire&lt;/em&gt; will rapidly and spontaneously be constructed and defended. In this natural and obvious urgency, bad faith will occasionally out itself in slips of the tongue whereby academics, such as a one David Golumbia, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/dgolumbia/status/848538857331191809&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;proudly and explicitly reveal their commitment to anti-intellectual tactics.&lt;/a&gt; You might think that rallying around such a patently unintellectual position typically associated with bourgeois-conservative simpletons would itself be avoided as an existential threat just as well, for it loudly publicizes a scandalous dearth of the very intellectual firepower on which our status and salaries are supposed to depend. That respectable bourgeois intellectual culture would seek to stave off one existential threat through the symbolic equivalent of a kamikaze gambit reflects a secret awareness of its own doomed nature.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Capitalism is an instance, not an essence</title>
      <link>/blog/2017/04/28/capitalism-is-an-instance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2017/04/28/capitalism-is-an-instance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Nick Land sometimes reads Deleuze and Guattari as if all the mechanisms theorized by them are mechanisms unique to capitalism. I’m going to argue that this is one of the many specific points in which the accelerationist question remains far from settled, and in which the foreclosing of revolutionary praxis strikes me as over-hasty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To Land, some of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xenosystems.net/re-accelerationism/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;D&amp;amp;G’s concepts are not just theoretically applicable to features of capitalism but strictly synonymous with them&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The D&amp;amp;G model of capitalism is not dialectical, but cybernetic, defined by a positive coupling of commercialization (“decoding”) and industrialization (“Deterritorialization”), intrinsically tending to an extreme (or “absolute limit”). Capitalism is the singular historical installation of a social machine based upon cybernetic escalation (positive feedback), reproducing itself only incidentally, as an accident of continuous socio-industrial revolution. Nothing brought to bear against capitalism can compare to the intrinsic antagonism it directs towards its own actuality, as it speeds out of itself, hurtling to the end already operative ‘within’ it. (Of course, this is madness.)”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is reasonable enough because capitalism certainly provides the most stunning and historically consequential examples of these mechanisms. But this is effectively a form of selection bias. This thing we call capitalism is only the contingent world-historical catastrophe that has made us conscious of these mechanisms through our feeling the violent long-run effects of them having over-taken us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole point of D&amp;amp;G’s project, in my view, is to identify very general mechanisms; such that they can serviceably explain the perpetuation of systemic oppressions but also serve as actionable maps for spinning new, non-linear systemic dynamics (world-historical transitions) from the most micro-scopic mechanisms. If “decoding” meant “commercialization,” why are their texts otherwise quite clearly anti-capitalist? In other words, while I think these readings of D&amp;amp;G are often quite brilliant and productive, the current frontiers of accelerationism have something of a problem around “face validity.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the biographical evidence makes it very hard to fathom that D or G intended any kind of passive capitulationism, and their works are a brilliant catalogue of calls to activity. Their writings are filled with injunctions such as, “Always follow the rhizome by rupture; lengthen, prolong, and relay the line of flight,” etc. Am I really to imagine that all of these lines are trying to tell me that I should start a business? I am not dismissing the provocative capitalist reading of D&amp;amp;G, I am only pointing out the obvious (which is surprisingly glossed over by the current frontiers of accelerationsim): D&amp;amp;G’s call to accelerate seemed pretty clearly to be part of a larger vision in which any interested party could learn how to accelerate into liberation from the inertia of systemic oppression; that the other side is more desirable, and that we might even find each other there together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not saying that the passivism or “horrorism” of Landian or unconditional accelerationism (i.e., there’s basically nothing for us to do) is not possibly the correct, final conclusion that D&amp;amp;G were simply incapable of drawing; it is only to say that, insofar as accelerationism is premised on D&amp;amp;G, passivist interpretations should explain why D&amp;amp;G spent so much effort delineating all of those general mechanisms in a general way, with so many inspiriting exhortations, if not to use them for liberatory ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many want to conclude that the call to accelerate forecloses revolutionary praxis, but one of the seminal projects underwriting the accelerationist turn, that of D&amp;amp;G, is filled with micro-models of how to produce macro-phenomena. Accelerating, in my view, means actively pursuing these threads, only faster. I do not see any strong reasons why, in D&amp;amp;G, the call to accelerate must necessarily imply a sharp exit from the project of fundamentally changing the world through revolutionary action—unless you define D&amp;amp;G’s concepts as essentially beginning and ending with capitalism. And I see no reason for doing that, other than a selection bias in which we are overweighting the reality of capitalism simply because it’s the phenomenon through which we first saw certain general mechanisms to work on planetary scale.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The formal structure of paranoid leftism (why there is no such thing as a noble error)</title>
      <link>/blog/2017/04/24/the-formal-structure-of-paranoid-leftism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2017/04/24/the-formal-structure-of-paranoid-leftism/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;People who want to think, write, or act outside of what is perceived as normal within currently consituted left-wing circles are now commonly talked about as possible fascist sympathizers. Typically, if you drill down into what is being said exactly, they are not accused of being fascists, they are accused of not clearly enough differentiating themselves from fascism, to a degree that exceeds the currently established expectations of what anti-fascism is believed to look like. When you drill down, the root of the problem (and sometimes admittedly) is reputation: “I know you’re not a fascist but these other people will wonder, ergo I must disavow you as inadequately anti-fascist.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that this model of changing the culture is premised on the willful acceptance and promotion of &lt;em&gt;incorrect judgments.&lt;/em&gt; Contemporary left culture is premised on the belief that you can change the world through noble mistakes. But as a rule, you cannot change the world for the better by agreeing to make mistakes. You will either fail to change anything because you are operating in a fantasy land, or you will make the world much worse as you try to forcibly deform it around your mistakes. There is no such thing as a noble error. Every error or mistaken judgment that is tolerated or promoted in left culture as “solidarity,” will directly and demonstrably lead to a decreased probability of achieving equality and freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have tried to make this argument in the past but typically to closed ears, the purpose of this post is to demonstrate the problem in the clearest, most demonstrable and undeniable fashion, using some basic concepts from my background as a social scientist. Basically, the issue is that for human beings errors are unavoidable, but there are different types of errors and whether we like it or not we make choices about which types of errors we are more or less willing to accept before acting on a judgment. Even more usefully, we can generate some predictions about future outcomes based on which types of errors we decide to be comfortable with. Currently, left culture is deeply invested in reducing one type of error while it is almost infinitely comfortable with a different type of error. As I try to show below, the only possible result is that membership in the organized radical left must ultimately drop to zero, a process I believe is currently underway. I am also able to generate some predictions about the temporal shape of this extinction event that I fear is currently underway. I believe that soon this post will not even be necessary, as the predicted outcomes I outline below come true; but as these outcomes have not yet fully arrived, it is my wager that posts such as this might be enough to make the currently doomed strategies collapse once and for all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will focus on the particular example of anti-fascism because it offers an attractively simple and well-known structure of left/right group differentiation. But everything I say here can be applied to a variety of attitudes and behaviors dominant in left culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;two-different-types-of-error-and-the-example-of-anti-fascism&#34;&gt;Two different types of error and the example of anti-fascism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists distinguish between Type 1 errors (false positives, you think something exists when it really doesn’t) and Type 2 errors (false negatives, you think something is not there when it really is). If you are one of those people who genuinely believe there is no objective reality outside of our interpretations of it, buckle up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever we are confronted with a question about something in the world, there is some risk of both types of error. If you maybe just saw a snake in the bush, there is some probability you are right and some probability you are wrong. And you &lt;em&gt;have to&lt;/em&gt; decide what to do, so what’s at stake here is not some obscure scientific theory: I am talking about basic unavoidable challenges of being a human. We can either do them intelligently and act on the world effectively (dodge snakes when they are there and relax when they are not there), or we can pretend we don’t have to grapple with them and basically sign-up to be helpless victims of our environment (never really run and never really relax, but just accept you’re probably going to get eaten by a python eventually so whatever).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This scenario is exactly analogous to the problem of anti-fascism. If there is someone in our movement for collective equality who is actually sympathetic to fascism or likely to say/do things that help fascism, then we probably won’t want to work with them. This is reasonable enough, and it is widely seen as a serious and urgent issue. But there is also another problem, which is symptomatically not discussed as very urgent or serious, which is that you will sometimes incorrectly refuse to work with someone who actually, on net, would help your team get to where it’s trying to go. People on the left like to act like this is not a genuine problem of judgment; it’s just how things are, there are norms, if someone wants to break those norms, then they can’t work with left groups, “it’s not up to me.” But that’s what Sartre called bad faith. It is up to you, it’s unavoidably up to everyone in the struggle for political change to decide who you will and who you will not work with. Everyone on the radical left has to make individual and group judgments that carry an unavoidable risk of being false, either failing to eject forces of harm or ejecting forces of good. You can also easily see how this basic structure is observed in many other particular questions of how to conduct ourselves in trying to produce social change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we think we might have seen a snake—we think someone in our groups will do more harm to our project than good—but we can’t know for sure. The idea that person X is basically good and would be a net contributor to collective liberation if we worked togetehr, we will call that the “null hypothesis” (usually denoted H0). The idea that person X would be a net detractor of the project for collective liberation if allowed to remain in the group, and should therefore be labeled as outside the project for public relations purposes, we will call the “alternative hypothesis” (usually denoted H1). For any person, there must exist some distribution that defines the probability of each scenario being true. Imagine it looks like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4177/33399772074_1b11d1fb45_b.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A visual representation of the trade-off between Type 1 and Type 2 errors&#34; title=&#34;A visual representation of the trade-off between Type 1 and Type 2 errors&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overlap of the two distributions reflects a trade-off between false positive and false negatives. If you are really concerned to make one type of error as unlikely as possible, you increase the probability of the other. We can never know for sure, so the idea of being exactly right in every case is not possible. So we have to decide the threshold of confidence we need to exclude someone from our group. Are we comfortable with a 5% chance of being incorrect? A 50% chance of being incorrect? In the graph above, “any mean” refers to how often you are willing to be wrong after operating on your judgment over a large number of cases. To decide how comfortable we should be with false positives and false negatives, we need to have a sense of the costs of each type of error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the real cost of an undetected fascist being in our group?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the real cost of ejecting someone who could and would help make revolution?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, these are very interesting and highly debatable questions. Future revolutionaries will need to devote themselve to answering these questions. At present, the main point to understand is that contemporary left culture does not think, let alone debate, these questions. Current left culture operates on the assumption the cost of a false negative is &lt;em&gt;very high&lt;/em&gt; and that the cost of false positives is &lt;em&gt;very low&lt;/em&gt;. It doesn’t take a social scientist to predict what will happen: you will be very effective in making sure no Nazis are hiding in your groups, but you will also ensure that many good people are pushed out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-non-linear-temporal-dynamics-of-paranoid-leftism&#34;&gt;The non-linear temporal dynamics of paranoid leftism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what will happen if we operate on this set of assumptions? Let’s say we start out with a nice sizeable number of anti-fascist comrades, 100, say. At first, maybe you find some people on the street who kind of look like Nazis so you tell them they can’t be in your movement and they go home very sad. These people turn out to be good people, so in fact you lost a few potential supporters but your group is still 100 people, so no big deal. Those poor guys are expendable, an unfortunate cost of your noble responsibility to keep the streets clean. But a few weeks later someone accuses one of your own member of having fascist sympathies, so the group decides to eject them. Turns out they were a secret member of the KKK, so everyone is delighted at their good judgment! You decide that everyone should be even more on guard to fascists, so you increase your allowable Type 1 error rate even higher. So the next week you kick out two members who later turn out to be good people who would have done much more good than harm had they stayed in the group. Here, the power of your group decreases concretely, due to your errors, but only a little bit. It decreases by a quantity of 2 power units, say, the lost power of those two people. Some concerns about this are raised within the group, but everyone decides it’s just an unfortunate byproduct of keeping the group safe. This is where you start to get non-linear effects that very few radicals want to think about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, some of the other good people in the group realize &lt;em&gt;there is a decent chance I will become a false positive.&lt;/em&gt; Realizing this, they either leave the group out of very reasonable fear of being unfairly and incorrectly maligned, or if leaving is not an option (if, for instance, their identity and relationships are dependent on the radical left milieu), what will they do? They will do everything they can to &lt;em&gt;find a fascist in their midst,&lt;/em&gt; to demonstrate to their group their fearless and passionate anti-fascist credibility! Fortunately, since they believe nothing bad really happens if we incorrectly diagnose a good person as fascist, protecting their anti-fascist credibility is not even a very taxing task: just take your best guess among any other member, if they are a fascist you’re a vigilant hero and if they are not, well that’s just an unavoidable byproduct of you valiantly keeping the group safe. Well, to see the outcome of this situation, consider the following figure, which plots the predicted size of your noble left project as a function of your comfort with false positives. The inflection point where the size of your group rapidly plunges toward zero can be thought of as that false-positive error-rate at which good members have good reason to fear being incorrectly labeled fascist. As soon as that happens, the whole project is doomed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c1.staticflickr.com/3/2917/34110622501_35db86df0c_b.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The hypothesized non-linear effect of over-zealous enemy identification on movement size&#34; title=&#34;The hypothesized non-linear effect of over-zealous enemy identification on movement size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paranoid leftism can be formally defined as the pathological insistence on sub-optimally high Type 1 error rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is only one non-obvious extension I would like to make. I believe the internet exacerbates the problem of under-estimating the cost of false-positives. Why? For the simple reason that the internet increases the number of people one can communicate and establish affiliations with, and there are a very small number of fascists relative to the number of good people, all of whom we have more or less equal and direct access to. Radicals have to remember that everything they say and do has effects not only on every individual we interact with, but also, rapidly, on the large number of individuals that individual interacts with. So reputational effects cut both ways: ejecting good people as inadequately anti-fascist loses trust among many people who simply do not inform you about it. If you accidentally eject one good person for being inadequately anti-fascist, you will lose the trust of the much larger group of people who trust that person, but who just happen to be sociologically distant from you. Therefore paranoid anti-fascism pretends to be about preserving trust with oppressed people but it’s really about avoiding difficult conversations with socially proximate actors. False positives patently destroy trust toward the very notion of organizing radical social change. Most people in the wealthy countries come to see radical groups as ridiculous losers with no credibility, in part because we run around eating our own in ways that anyone other than us can see to be stupid and insane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paranoid leftist values their own discomfort with impurity and their own reputation within a small miliue more than the prospect of generating large-scale, emancipatory, cultural dynamics tending toward the dissolution of fascism and the promotion of egalitarianism and abundance. The neo-Nazi is a fascist of the short-run; the paranoid leftist is a fascist of the long-run. It is a way of being so concerned with signaling the appearance of opposition to Bad People that you would rather see the power of your own movement decrease than assume the responsibility of simply explaining one’s reasoned judgments in difficult conversations with a small number of people who might be “concerned.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on some rare Deleuze lectures</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/11/22/notes-on-rare-deleuze-lectures/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/11/22/notes-on-rare-deleuze-lectures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 1975-76, a student named Marielle Burkhalter recorded video of Gilles Deleuze’s lectures at the University of Paris VIII in Vincennes. Some of the video has been translated and re-presented by a couple of artists named Silvia Maglioni and Graeme Thomson, in an on-going project called &lt;em&gt;Through the Letterbox.&lt;/em&gt; In &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.whitechapelgallery.org/events/a-life-beyond-the-facts-deleuze-now/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;a recent showing at the Whitechapel Gallery&lt;/a&gt; in London, I got to watch a set of clips with English subtitles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The videos were extraordinary. My French would not have been nearly good enough to get much from them had it not been for the subtitles. But the subtitles felt very well done. He is very intense and improvisational but faster and less self-important than someone like Lacan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it felt like quite a rare privilege to watch these lectures—and as far as I can find, these particular clips with subtitles are not currently available online—I took some fairly detailed notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pretty sure it is fair to say these may be some of the only notes in English on this particular set of lectures in 1975-76.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presumably thanks to the curation, these clips were highly condensed around some of the most important and productive points in Deleuze’s perspective. Some ideas which in the books are very difficult are here made really quite simple; to a degree that is quite remarkable and, I think, almost surprisingly useful and helpful—especially from a political perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below I attach some fairly unedited notes. Minor personal comments are in square brackets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t derive a bridge from a filiation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Filiation would ruin everything, would only be connecting kingdoms&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bridge is a term of alliance&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Micromultiplicities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communication between two completely separate lines&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A virus connects different series which do not therefore become one (i.e., a bridge rather than a filiation)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;So connections between separate lines create multiplicities&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;swarm of black holes is different than a molar ensemble because each is emitter and receiver, no hierarchical structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Here he is turning to the question of how you can link up several micromultiplicities, the question of “good” or perhaps we might say desirable scaling-up and aggregation, as opposed to “bad” (hierarchy and domination). He does not explain what he means by black hole but it’s elaborated at length in &lt;em&gt;Mille Plateaux&lt;/em&gt;. In short, I read it as a void at the center of all structures, a kind of perhaps necessary anchoring point but one which typically comes to be associated with illusory meanings and conservative collective investments. He also calls it the “face,” which I think is related to how the face is the black hole of modern, narcissistic-individualistic bourgeois subjectivity (it anchors so much meaning for us and is yet ultimately empty). I would say the “black hole” or “face” is quite similar to what Lacan has in mind with his concept of the &lt;em&gt;point de capiton,&lt;/em&gt; but I’m not an expert. In any event, in this opaque last point he is basically saying that a micromultiplicity of black holes is in less danger of fascistic regression because no particular black hole has any more power than another. There is also a connotation, I think, of relative transparency (the language of communication), as compared to the black holes of molar multiplicities, as below.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any molar multiplicitly, something, another nature is slipping in&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throwing down bridges, connecting new loops and networks&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How is a multiplicity defined?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Molar multiplicity = structuring principle that is not given as such&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But crafty multiplicities, discreet multiplicities that insinuate themselves, that’s not a structuring principle (talked about this last year)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of dimensions. But how do we understand how many? They have a &lt;em&gt;maximal&lt;/em&gt; dimension. &lt;em&gt;This is where it gets interesting&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[He really emphasizes this last point. He is very excited about it.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The maximum dimension possible. That is it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The maximum dimension is called the border, and that is where we are saved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of a secret organizing principle, like in molar ensembles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a “fly” or “frog” multiplicity, or a mosquito multiplicity. Finally, remaining in science instead of literature. One fly means nothing. A single fly is lost, aka not a fly. All that means anything is “flies”. A wolf means nothing. A lone wolf means nothing, but if it’s the border wolf then that’s different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moby Dick: the border&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The border animal is always a monster, that’s important&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Power apparatuses&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Micromultiplicity is a molecular multiplicity, a swarm, aleatory&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every mosquito is the border, all can see the others in space&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The limit is to have all mosquitos to the right, for instance, at which point they tend to back in. Stability is assured in case of catastrophe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The border: the line in function of which you see all others on the other side&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take advantage of being on the border&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means being part of the gang, while not being in it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside then re-entering&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it &lt;em&gt;Morphogensis&lt;/em&gt; by Thom, or &lt;em&gt;Morphogenology&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[I think he is asking Guattari in the audience, or suggesting that Guattari be consulted or something, not sure. In any event he is referring to &lt;em&gt;Structural Stability and Morphogenesis&lt;/em&gt; by René Thom.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Mrs. Dalloway&lt;/em&gt;, Virginia Woolf’s molar problems are solved by a walk. No longer the same scale. A fantastic molecular walk sweeps away the molar problems, e.g. to remain man or woman, to marry or not, molar problems. A small particle makes all this explode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During her walk among taxis; taxis are semi-aleatory&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She slices like a “knife through everything”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am a mist”, she says. That’s a molecular multiplicity&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A mist laid out among the people I know”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And at the same time, I am on the outside&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How is that possible? It’s odd, you cant describe that as a molar thing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will say “it’s only literature”, “you’re either outside or inside.” You’re either one of us or you’re out, or you’ve been placed on sentry duty. Or there is a series of binary choices…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will say “you can’t say that” (like logical postivism).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we can awake particles, and nobody can deny that. “But of course, this is how I live.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A particle that is always on the border of the multiplicity it belongs to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it can be any particle whatsoever, like mosquitos, or it can be a monster mosquito, Moby Dick, head wolf. If you find the border, you’ll know how many dimensions the multiplicity has. If you dont keep to the border, you are stuck in the molar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A rapport between lines of flight and border, perhaps the border is a path. The particles on the border stabilize. Temporary stabilizer. Local, but not only. It also lets the mult slip into another. It is stabilized, but also puts the border near others, and allows them to transform. Thresholds or doors from one border to another, below a threshold, the border defines the local stabliizer. Above it, there is tranformation into the other. A slippage of borders, an overcoming of thresholds. No ramified arborescent schema can do that. “Sol-gel,” from state of solution to a gel. The solution state is a kind of multiplicity, the gel is another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does a border pass the threshold? The percolation threshold. You can’t do this with an aborescent model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[I put in my notes, “This really matters for how we see the wealthy, the politicos, etc. We tend to see them as powerful and in control but I really think nearly the opposite, and I have been trying to think harder about what it means if we take that very seriously. I think Deleuze is helping to explain that the powerful are not in control but really they are stuck more than anyone, at least in one special sense; they couldn’t change themselves or their environments even if they wanted to or tried, because they are so in the center of the molar ensembles, they are indeed only those who have been most fully sucked into the molar black hole.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bordering particles have to change nature, &lt;em&gt;“that’s key”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Species or types dont matter to evolutionary theorists, only populations&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Debts, counter-debts: these are bonds&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All individual lines on their own terms&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Threateend by massification or leadership on the inside, or group oedipus, like gender roles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gangs are molecular multiplicities&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then they are threatened by the molar, like how nomads become states&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is that the individuals go out, they bring back the loot, and redistribute it. But it’s always on individuals terms. There are debts and alliances, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[To be clear, I think he is saying “it’s always on individual terms” as if it’s a good thing; i.e. autonomy.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But black holes can emerge on the inside of a gang; the issue is to not slip over into the molar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Molar ensembles are organized around black holes or the face; it organizes the center by organizing ambitions, all the underlings try to enter the center, because those are the careers which are legitimated; the value and reality of different goals are decided by the structuring of the moral ensembles, it sucks everything in as a black hole does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[I think it was my own note here, that I wrote: “A constant sucking up of our &lt;em&gt;attention.&lt;/em&gt; I don’t remember him using the word “attention” so I think that was me, but it could have been him, I forget.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except the sentrys who are charged with guarding&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outsider can come from nowhere, overspilling the border, the unnameable thing, a swarm of one&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leader of a molecular multiplicity, they are inherently on a border. As in animal packs, a central leader, and someone who pushes, surveys, the great nomad; only emporers stay in the center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is always what kind of leader: a border-dweller occupying postion of outsider, or a “champion” of centralized power, a face.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A theory of ethically-biased technological change (toward an empirical test of the Frankfurt School)</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/06/21/a-theory-of-ethically-biased-technological-change-toward-an-empirical-test-of-the-frankfurt-school/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/06/21/a-theory-of-ethically-biased-technological-change-toward-an-empirical-test-of-the-frankfurt-school/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h5 id=&#34;the-puzzle&#34;&gt;The Puzzle&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a widespread consensus in the economics literature that the rise of information technology over the past several decades has been a “skill-biased technological change.” A skill-biased technological change increases the productivity of skilled workers more than it improves the productivity of unskilled workers, therefore increasing the demand for skilled workers relative to unskilled workers. This increased demand for skilled workers, ceteris paribus, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dictionaryofeconomics.com/article?id=pde2008_S000493&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;increases their income relative to unskilled workers&lt;/a&gt;. It is widely agreed that this is a key explanation for at least some of the rapid increase in income inequality since the 1980s.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; One key observation consistent with this theory is that it is only after the appearance of micro-computers that income inequality begins to rise in the early 1980s.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A second key observation is that more educated workers are more likely to use a computer on the job&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite this growing interest in the economic implications of technological change, social scientists have failed to take seriously a surprisingly similar line of thought advanced most notably in twentieth-century German philosophy. Heidegger and, later, the Frankfurt School theorists developed critical theories of technology which argued, in different ways, that technological changes shape ethical attitudes toward the world. In particular, a specific line of thought revolves around the relationship between technological development and instrumental rationality, or in other words formal analytical rationality which renounces consideration of substantive goals and concerns itself only with calculating the optimal means toward given ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Heidegger, from a phenomenological perspective, technology represents a &amp;ldquo;clearing&amp;rdquo; of Being which generates a relation to the world in which nature and other humans are merely &amp;ldquo;standing-reserve&amp;rdquo; waiting to be exploited as means to whatever ends. For Adorno, Horkheimer, and especially Marcuse, modern technological advancements were &amp;ldquo;organizing and perpetuating (or changing) social relationships, a manifestation of prevalent thought and behavior patterns, an instrument for control and domination.”&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While positivist social scientists have long perceived these types of claims from continential social theory to be hopelessly speculative and empirically intractable, this is puzzling given that the core claim emerging from this particular current in the critical theory of technology is relatively straightforward: technological development increases the prevalence of instrumentalism among other possible ethical attitudes toward the world. Moreover, the theory of skill-biased technological change is a powerful heuristic for modeling this argument given that it is a well-established model of how technology can generate unequal distributions of power without any reference to Marxian bugaboos which have likely caused more confusion than clarity by now.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is perhaps more fair to observe that critical theorists indeed sometimes lack what contemporary social scientists would call “mechanisms,&amp;rdquo; or specifiable and testable triggers which effectively do the work of some variable &lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt; supposedly causing some variable &lt;em&gt;Y&lt;/em&gt;. While this particular critique of technological development is not delivered with any particular &amp;ldquo;mechanism&amp;rdquo; which would be intelligible to many empirical social scientists working today, critical theory does supply many useful hints in this direction. Moreover, the basic argument is surprisingly consistent with well-known economic models, however disparate might be the vocabularies, thus permitting the elaboration of a critical theory of technological change empirically testable and consistent with a rational-choice framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;a-theory&#34;&gt;A Theory&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To better specify the mechanism whereby technological change may plausibly generate a greater prevalence of instrumental ethics, I propose a theory of &lt;em&gt;ethically-biased&lt;/em&gt; technological change. I argue that certain technological changes can increase the income paid to certain ethical orientations relative to others. As in the theory of skill-biased technological change, certain technological changes increase the productivity of certain ethical orientations relative to others, increasing their relative demand, and therefore increasing their relative income. This increase in relative income represents a premium paid to those with the ethical resources required by the new technology, just as skill-biased technological change generates a premium paid to those with the technical resources required by the new technology.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More specifically, a technological change which increases productivity but transgresses &lt;em&gt;any particular ethical value&lt;/em&gt; will increase the productivity of individuals with the weakest commitment to that ethical value relative to those more firmly committed to that ethical value, thus increasing demand for them relative to the more ethical individuals, and thereby increasing their relative income. Ethically transgressive technological innovations increase the productivity of the least ethical because ethical compunctions are effectively a psychological tax on a worker. It is hard to take a job, and then demoralizing to work it, to the degree one feels ethical compunction for doing so. While an employer would have to pay very high wages to attract highly ethical workers to an ethically transgressive job, the wages they have to pay to attract relatively unethical workers will tend to be lower. The firmer one&amp;rsquo;s ethical commitment, the greater is the tax one pays to work an ethically transgressive job, the less worthwhile the wage, and the less likely is one to take the job; the weaker one&amp;rsquo;s ethical commitment, the lower is the tax, the more worthwhile is the wage, and the more likely one is to take the job. The overall implication is that technological change rewards individuals with weak ethical convictions relative to individuals with strong ethical convictions, and therefore exerts a direct, material pressure on the evolution of ethics within society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three key, testable implications we would expect to observe if this model indeed captures important aspects of the historical record. First, during times of ethically transgressive technological innovation, the first workers will be individuals who before the technological innovation were already less ethically scrupulous on the relevant ethical dimension. Second, workers of the new technology will be paid a premium which would be, in principle, distinct from any skill premium, although of course these can be correlated. Third, if we add the assumption of modern capitalist institutions, wherein wage workers have no common land and no immediate means of production, then the price of integrity for committedly ethical individuals literally becomes death. This last implication means that, if technological change is ethically biased as I hypothesize, the steady-state to which it must tend in the long-run is the absolute evacuation of integrity from all participants in the labor market. Note that this can come about through two different causal pathways: ethical individuals can learn to sacrifice their integrity to compete with the unethical and survive, &lt;em&gt;and/or&lt;/em&gt; ethical individuals can literally die off while unethical individuals thrive and replace them (evolutionary change). It should be noted explicitly that while observations 1 and 2 show how ethically-biased technological change reward certain ethical orientations differently and unequally,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anecdotally, a general acquaintenace with the contours of modern history seems to suggest some striking evidence for this model of ethically-biased technology change. Consider, for instance, that while a certain amount of philosophical liberalism was no doubt necessary for the industrial revolution to emerge, and this perhaps explains why it began in England, it seems equally undeniable that the industrial revolution in turn &lt;em&gt;generated&lt;/em&gt; an extraordinary instrumental turn and valorization of self-interest wherever it went. It will obviously require more work to test this expectation more rigorously, but it seems highly probable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, building from insights of the Frankfurt School, I provide a specific, empirically testable mechanism which accounts for the large-scale historical variations in ethical outlook they described to the dismissal of the mainstream social scientists of the time. Working heuristically from rational-choice economic theory, my stylized theoretical model is consistent with but more general than the rational-choice framework because the model here in some sense explains what rational-choice models merely assume (the prevalance of instrumentally rational dispositions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If correct, the long-run, world-historical implication of this model could not be more staggering for understanding the ethical experience of living through modern, let alone contemporary, capitalism: if this model is correct, then it would mean that today we have inherited a world in which ethical integrity has been subjected to a roughly 300-500 year forced evacuation by labor market institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;See Card, David, and John E DiNardo. 2002. “Skill Biased Technological Change and Rising Wage Inequality: Some Problems and Puzzles” and Guvenen, Fatih, and Burhanettin Kuruscu. 2010. “A Quantitative Analysis of the Evolution of the U.S. Wage Distribution, 1970–2000.” NBER Macroeconomics Annual 24(1): 227–76.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Katz, Lawrence F. 2002. “Technological Change, Computerization, and the Wage Structure.” In Understanding the Digital Economy Data, Tools, and Research, Cambridge: MIT Press.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Autor, David H, Lawrence F Katz, and Alan B Krueger. 1997. “Computing Inequality: Have Computers Changed the Labor Market?”
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Marcuse, H. 1941. “Some Social Implications of Modern Technology.” Studies in Philosophy and Social Science, Vol. IX.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;I have in mind such perennial bad habits as lazily but self-certainly referring to Capital as a conspiratorial agent, an argument which has never boded very well for Marxism.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;Indeed, the analogy between skill-biased and ethically-biased technological change is all the more apt if we, with Foucault, conceptualize the practice of ethos as itself a kind of technical game; if ethical resources are themselves understood as technologies of the self. Key examples in this context are those most bourgeois of ethical resources: the various techniques of repressing ethical compunctions and moral anxieties, and the various techniques of guilt management consequently required by this ethos. In this register, ethically-biased technological change would be essentially identical to skill-biased technological with the exception that the &amp;ldquo;skills&amp;rdquo; in question are the skills of self-management rather than economic production. The reason we must avoid this reductionism at the outset is that it would beg the most important question, namely, the question regarding &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; exactly did the contemporary human become, quite peculiar in the long-run of world history, so instrumentalist that the only activities remaining in contemporary life are exploiting and suffering exploitation?
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A diagram of stratification</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/12/19/dg-stratifcation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/12/19/dg-stratifcation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Below is a sketch of what Deleuze and Guattari describe as &amp;ldquo;the pincer&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;double articulation&amp;rdquo; of stratification.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://wl.figshare.com/articles/881284/embed?show_title=0&#34; width=&#34;650&#34; height=&#34;424&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;   

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Deleuze, Gilles, and Félix Guattari. 1987. &lt;em&gt;A Thousand Plateaus.&lt;/em&gt; Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press. pp. 40-41.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
